I have been a police officer for a very, very long time.
لقد كنت شرطيا لمدة طويلة جدا.
And you see these notes in my hand because I'm also a black preacher.
وأترون هذه الأوراق في يدي هنا لأنني واعظ من عرق أسود.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And if you know anything about black preachers,
وإن كنتم تعلمون أي شيء عن واعظ من عرق أسود،
we'll close, and then we'll keep going for another 20 minutes.
فنحن قريبين من الموضوع وسنستمرّ في الحديث لمدة 20 دقيقة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I need this to keep pushing this thing forward.
إذن أنا في حاجة إلى استمرار هذا الأمر.
I've been a police officer for a very long time,
لقد كنت شرطيا لمدة طويلة من الزمن،
and I mean I predated technology.
وأعني بأنني كنت سابقا للتكنولوجيا.
I'm talking about before pagers.
أنا أتحدث قبل ظهور أجهزة النداء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Laugh if you want to, but I'm telling the truth.
اضحكوا إن أردتم ذلك ولكنني أقول الحقيقة.
I predate War on Our Fellow Man -- I mean, War on Drugs.
لقد كنت سابقا للحرب على زميلنا -- أعني، الحرب على المخدرات.
I predate all of that.
لقد كنت سابقا لكل هذا.
I predate so much
كنت سابقا كثيرا
and I've been through ebbs and flows
ولقد واجهت أوقاتا صعبة وأخرى سهلة
and I've been through good and bad times,
وأوقاتا جيدة وأخرى سيئة،
and still I absolutely love being a police officer.
ولكن مع ذلك مازلت أحب مهنتي كشرطي.
I love being a police officer because it's always been a calling for me
أحب مهنتي كشرطي لأن ذلك بالنسبة لي هو واجب
and never a job.
وليس عمل.
And even with that,
ولكن مع ذلك،
my personal truth is that law enforcement is in a crisis.
الحقيقة الشخصية أن تطبيق القانون في أزمة.
It's an invisible crisis,
أزمة غير مرئية،
and it has been for many, many years.
ولقد وجدت هذه الأزمة منذ العديد والعديد من السنوات.
Even though we in law enforcement say,
بالرغم من أننا عند تطبيق القانون نقول،
"You know what? We can't arrest our way out of this."
"أتعرف؟ نحن لا نستطيع اعتقالك ليس لنا الحق في ذلك."
We say in law enforcement things like,
في تطبيق القانون نقول أشياء مثل ،
"Yeah, it's illegal to profile."
"نعم، الكشف عن معلومات شخصية لشخص ما غير قانوني."
You know what?
أتعرفون؟
In law enforcement, we even agree that we have to adopt this thinking
عند تطبيق القانون، نحن نتفق على اعتماد هذا التفكير
and become more oriented to community policing.
ونتجه أكثر إلى الشرطة المجتمعية.
And yet all the while, still,
ولكن مع ذلك، ما نزال،
we continue in the same vein,
مستمرين بالعمل على نفس المنوال،
the same vein that contradicts everything that we just admitted.
نفس المنوال الذي يتناقض مع كل شيء اعترفنا به.
And so that's the reason for me, several years ago.
وذلك هو السبب بالنسبة لي، منذ عدة سنوات مضت.
Because I was tired of the racism, I was tired of discrimination,
لأنني تعبت من العنصرية، وتعبت من التمييز،
I was tired of the "-isms" and the schisms.
لقد تعبت من "انشق" والانشقاقات الدينية.
I was just so tired.
لقد كنت متعبا حقا.
I was tired of the vicious cycle,
لقد كنت متعبا من الحلقة المفرغة،
and I was tired of it even in the beloved agency
ولقد كنت متعبا من ذلك حتى بالوكالة المحببة لي
in the department that I still love today.
في القسم الذي مازلت أحبه إلى الآن.
And so my wife and I, we sat down
ولقد جلست أنا وزوجتي،
and we decided and we targeted a date that we would retire.
وقررنا اليوم الذي سنتقاعد فيه.
We would retire and I would go off into the sunset,
سنتقاعد وسوف أذهب لمشاهدة غروب الشمس،
maybe do ministry full time, love my wife a long time.
أو أقوم بدور الوزير، أو أحب زوجتي أكثر.
Y'all know what I'm talking about.
أنتم تعرفون ما الذي أتحدث عنه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But we decided that I would retire.
ولكن قررنا بأنني سأتقاعد.
But then there was a higher power than I.
لكن كانت هناك قوة أقوى مني.
There was a love for the city
كان هناك نوع من الحب للمدينة
that I loved, that I grew up in, that I was educated in --
التي أحببتها وتررعت بها ودرست فيها--
a city that pulled my heart back into the system.
مدينة عادت بقلبي للنظام.
So we didn't retire.
لذلك لم نتقاعد.
We didn't retire
لم نتقاعد
and so what happened was,
والذي حصل،
over the next -- I would say, 18 months, 19 months,
بعد --سأقول، 18 شهرا، 19 شهرا
I had this passion to implement some radical policing.
لقد كانت لدي تلك الرغبة لتنفيذ مراقبة جذريّة.
And so now, over the next 19 months,
والآن نحن في فترة تتجاوز 19 شهرا،
I shifted, and I transcended from being a drug sergeant --
لقد غيرت الرتبة، وتحوّلت من رقيب مخدرات --
ready to retire as a drug sergeant --
إلى رقيب مخدرات مستعد للتقاعد--
and went from level to level to level,
وانتقلت من مستوى إلى مستوى آخر وإلى مستوى آخر،
until I find myself as a district commander,
إلى أن وجدت نفسي كقائد للمقاطعة،
commander of the worst district in Baltimore city.
قائد لأسوأ مقاطعة بمدينة بالتيمور.
We call it the Eastern District,
والتي نسميها المنطقة الشرقية،
the most violent district,
وهي المنطقة الأكثرعنفا،
the most impoverished district --
والمنطقة الأكثر فقرا --
46 percent unemployment in that district.
سجلت 46 % من البطالة بتلك المنطقة.
National rating at that time,
في ذلك الوقت المعدل الوطني
national rating, the AIDS and the tuberculosis [rating],
المعدل الوطني للإيدز والسلّ
was always on the top 10 list
كان دائما على رأس القائمة من ضمن الـ 10 الأوائل
for zip codes for cities across the nation,
للرموز البريدية للأحياء في جميع أنحاء البلاد،
or just zip codes across the nation.
أو فقط رموز بريدية في جميع أنحاء البلاد.
The top 10 -- I didn't say state, I didn't say city --
الـ 10 الأوائل -- لم أقل دولة، لم اقل مدينة --
that little neighborhood.
ذلك الحي الصغير.
And I said, you know what? We gotta do something different.
وقلت، هل تعرفون؟ علينا القيام بشيء مختلف.
We gotta think radical.
علينا التفكير بجذريّة.
We gotta think outside the box.
علينا التفكير خارج الصندوق.
And so in order to bring change that I desperately wanted
وبهدف تحقيق التغيير الذي أردته بشدّة
and I desperately felt in my heart,
والذي أحسست به.
I had to start listening to that inner spirit.
يجب أن أستمع إلى الصوت بداخلي.
to that man on the inside
ينبغي أن أبدأ في الاستماع إلى ذلك الرجل في الداخل
that went against everything that I had been trained to do.
الذي واجه كل شيء تدرب عليه.
But we still did it.
ولكن مازلنا نقوم به.
We still did it because we listened to that inner spirit,
مازلنا نقوم به لأننا نستمع إلى ذلك الصوت بداخلنا،
because I realized this:
لأنني أدركت التالي:
if I was to see real police reform
إذا أردت رؤية إصلاحا حقيقيا في قطاع الشرطة
in the communities that I had authority over for public safety,
في المجتمعات التي كنت أراقبها وأراقب سلامتها،
we had to change our stinkin' thinkin'.
علينا تغيير تفكيرنا.
We had to change it.
علينا تغييره.
And so what we did is we started to think holistically
إذن بدأنا في التفكير بصورة أشمل
and not paramilitarily.
وليس بطريقة شبه عسكرية.
So we thought differently.
إذن فكرنا بطريقة مختلفة.
And we started to realize
وبدأنا ندرك
that it could never be and never should have been
أنه لم يكن يجدر بنا أن
us versus them.
نكون نحن ضدهم.
And so I decided to come to that intersection
لذا قررت أن أستنتج ذلك التقاطع
where I could meet all classes, all races, all creeds, all colors;
حيت تعترضني جميع الفئات والأعراق والمذاهب والألوان،
where I would meet the businesses and the faith-based,
حيث يمكن أن تعترضني الأعمال والعقائد،
and the eds, the meds,
وأخصائي التعليم والأدوية،
and I would meet all the people
ويعترضني جميع الأشخاص
that made up the communities that I had authority over.
الذين كوّنوا المجتمعات التي أملك سلطة عليها.
So I met them and I began to listen.
لذا قابلتهم وبدأت في الاستماع إليهم.
See, police have a problem.
أترون، الشرطي لديه مشكلة.
Off the top, we want to bring things into the community
أولا، نريد توفير أشياء للمجتمع
and come up with these extravagant strategies and deployments,
وأن نأتي بهذه الاستراتيجيات المبالغ فيها،
but we never talk to the community about them.
ولكن لا نخبر المجتمعات عنها أبدا.
And we shove them into the community and say, "Take that."
ونقحمها في المجتمع ونقول "خذ هذا".
But we said we'd get rid of that stinkin' thinkin',
ولكننا قلنا بأننا سنتخلص من هذا التفكير الفاسد،
so we talked to our communities.
لذا تحدثنا إلى مجتمعاتنا.
We said, "This is your community table.
وقلنا، "هذه طاولة مجتمعك.
We'll pull up a chair. We want to hear from you.
سوف نسحب كرسي لك. نريد أن نسمع منك.
What's going to work in your community?"
ما الذي يمكنه أن يسير على ما يرام داخل مجتمعك؟"
And then some great things started to happen.
ثم بدأت أشياء رائعة بالظهور.
See, here's the thing:
أترون، هذا ما أتكلم عنه:
I had to figure out a way to shift 130 cops that were under my tutelage
كان عليّ أن أجد طريقة لتحويل 130 شرطيا تحت قيادتي
from being occupiers of communities
من محتلين للمجتمعات
to being partners.
إلى شركاء لهم.
I had to figure out how to do that.
عليّ أن أكتشف طريقة للقيام بذلك.
Because here's the crazy thing:
لأن الشيء المثير للجنون هنا هو:
in law enforcement, we have evolved into something incredible.
عند تطبيق القانون، تطورنا إلى شيء لا يُصدّق.
Listen, we have become great protectors.
اسمعوا، لقد أصبحنا حماة مذهلون.
We know how to protect you.
نحن نعرف كيفية حمايتكم.
But we have exercised that arm so much, so very much.
لقد دربنا هذا الساعد كثيرا وكثيرا.
If I was a natural police department
إذا كنت شرطيا بالقسم
and I represented a police department,
ومثّلت قسم الشرطة،
you would see this incredible, beautiful, 23-inch arm.
سوف ترون ذراع جميل 23 بوصة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's pretty, ain't it? It's cut up.
هذا جميل، أليس كذلك؟
No fat on it. Mmm it look good. It just look good!
لا دهن عليه. امم يبدو جيدا. إنه يبدو حقا جيدا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's a great arm -- protection!
هذا ساعد رائع -- حماية.
That's who we are, but we've exercised it so much sometimes
هذا ما نحن عليه، ولكن تدربنا كثيرا في بعض الأحيان
that it has led to abuse.
وهو ما أدى إلى الضرر.
It's led to coldness and callousness and dehumanized us.
وأدى إلى البرودة والقسوة وجردنا من إنسانيتنا.
And we've forgotten
ولقد نسينا
the mantra across this nation
الشعارالمتعلق بالدولة
is to protect and serve.
وهو الحماية والخدمة.
Y'all don't know that? Protect and serve.
أنتم لا تعرفون ذلك؟ الحماية والخدمة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So you look at the other arm,
إذن انظروا إلى الذراع الأخرى،
and then you look at it and ... there it is.
وثم تنظرون إليها و...هذا ماهي عليه.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know, it's kinda weak.
تعرفون، إنها ضعيفة نوعا ما.
It looks sickly.
تبدو مصابة بمرض.
It's withering and it's dying
إنها تذبل، إنها تموت
because we've invested so much in our protective arm.
لأننا استثمرنا الكثير في ذراعنا الحامية لنا.
But we forgot to treat our communities
ولكننا نسينا أن نعامل مجتمعاتنا
like they're our customers;
كزبائن لنا،
like they're our sons and daughters, our brothers and sisters,
كأبناءنا، كبناتنا وكإخواننا وكأخواتنا،
our mothers and fathers.
كأمهاتنا وكأباءنا.
And so somehow, along the way,
وبطريقة ما، في طريقنا،
we've gotten out of balance.
حدنا عن المسار.
And because we are a proud profession,
ولأن وظيفتنا فخر لنا،
it is very hard for us to look in the mirror and see our mistakes.
إنه من الصعب أن ننظر إلى المرآة وأن نعترف بأخطاءنا.
It's even harder to make a change.
إنه من الصعب حتى القيام بتغيير.
And so, as I try to hurry and get through this,
إذن، بينما أحاول جاهدا وبسرعة الخروج من هذا،
I need to say this:
أحتاج أن أقول التالي:
it's not just law enforcement, though.
إنه ليس مجرد تطبيق للقانون،
Because every one of us makes up a community.
لأن كل شخص فينا يُكوّن مجتمعا.
Everybody makes up a community.
الكلّ يُمثّل المجتمع.
And as communities -- can I say this? --
وكمجتمعات -- هل أستطيع أن أقول التالي؟
we have put too much responsibility on law enforcement.
لقد وضعنا مسؤولية كبيرة على تطبيق القانون.
Too much.
كبيرة جدا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And then we have the audacity and the nerve to get upset
ومن ثم لدينا الجرأة لكي نشعر بالحزن عند تطبيق القانون
with law enforcement when we take action.
وعند قيامنا بعملنا.
There is no way in the world
من المستحيل في العالم أجمع
that we, as a community, should be calling the police
كمجتمع أن نتصل بشرطي
for kids playing ball in the street.
لاطفال يلعبون بالكرة في الشارع.
No way in the world that we should be calling the police
من المستحيل في العالم أجمع كمجتمع أن نتصل بشرطي
because my neighbor's music is up too loud,
لأن الموسيقى في منزل الجيران صاخبة جدا،
because his dog came over to my yard and did a number two;
لأن كلبه تبرّز في حديقتي،
there's no way we should be calling the police.
لا يجدر بنا الاتصال بالشرطة.
But we have surrendered so much of our responsibility.
ولكننا تنازلنا كثيرا عن مسؤوليتنا.
Listen, when I was a little boy coming up in Baltimore --
استمعوا، عندما كنت طفلا صغيرا في بالتيمور --
and listen, we played rough in the street --
واستمعوا جيدا، لقد لعبنا كثيرا بالشوارع--
I ain't never see the police come and break us up.
ولم أرى شرطيا أتى ومنعنا من اللعب.
You know who came? It was the elders.
هل تعرفون من أتى؟ إنهم الكهول.
It was the parental figures in the community.
لقد كان الأباء بالمجتمع هم من يأتون.
It was those guardians, it was that village mentality.
لقد كانوا هؤلاء المسؤولين، لقد كانت تلك العقلية بالقرية.
They came and said, "Stop that!" and "Do this." and "Stop that."
كانوا يأتون ويقولون، "توقف عن ذلك" و "قم بهذا" و"توقف عن ذلك".
We had mentors throughout all of the community.
لقد كان لدينا معلمون من المجتمع كاملا.
So it takes all of us, all of us.
لذا ذلك يشملنا كلنا، كلنا.
And when I say community,
وعندما أقول المجتمع،
I'm talking about everything that makes up a community, even --
أنا أتحدث عن كل ما يُكوّن المجتمع، حتّى --
listen, because I'm a preacher, I'm very hard on the churches,
استمعوا --لأنني واعظ، أنا قاس جدا على الكنائس،
because I believe the churches too often have become MIA,
لأنني أؤمن بأنّ الكنائس غالبا ما أصبحت مفقودة في الحرب،
missing in action.
مفقودة في الحرب.
I believe they have shifted over the last 10, 20 years
أعتقد بأنهم تحولوا خلال 10 و20 سنة الأخيرة
from being community churches,
من كونهم كنائس للمجتمع،
where you walk outside your door, round the corner and you're in church.
أين تخرج من باب منزلك وتنعطف لتجد نفسك في الكنيسة.
They shifted from that and became commuter churches.
تغيروا ليصبحوا كنائس متنقلة.
So you now have churches who have become disconnected by default
إذن توجد الآن كنائس منعزلة
from the very community where they're planted.
عن المجتمع الذي توجد به.
And they don't take care of that community.
ولا يهمهم ذلك المجتمع.
I could go on and on, but I really need to wrap this up.
يمكنني المضي قدما، ولكنني يجب حقا أن أنهي هذا الموضوع.
Community and policing:
المجتمع والشرطة:
we've all lost that precious gift, and I call it relational equity.
لقد فقدنا كلنا تلك الهدية القيمة، والتي أسميها الإنصاف في العلاقات.
We've lost it with one another.
لقد فقدناها بيننا.
It's not somebody else's fault --
لا يُنسب هذا الخطأ إلى شخص آخر --
it's all of our fault.
هذا الخطأ هو خطئنا.
We all take responsibility in this.
جميعنا نتحمل المسؤولية في هذا.
But I say this: it's not too late for all of us to build our cities
ولكن أقول التالي: لم يفت الأوان بعد بالنسبة لنا لكي نبني مدننا
and nation to make it great again.
وبلادنا لكي تصبح رائعة من جديد.
It is never too late.
لم يفت الأوان بعد.
You see, after three years
أترون، بعد مرور 3 سنوات
of my four-and-a-half-year commandship in that district,
على عملي كقائد في تلك المنطقة لمدة 4 سنوات ونصف،
three years in,
3 سنوات،
after putting pastors in the car with my police
بعد وضع القساوسة بالسيارة مع الشرطي
because I knew this -- it's a little secret --
لأنني عرفت ذلك -- هو سرّ صغير --
I knew this:
عرفت التالي:
it was hard to stay a nasty police officer
من الصعب أن تظلّ شرطيّا سيّئا
while you're riding around with a clergy.
بينما تتجول مع رجل دين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
You'd be getting in and out of the car, looking to your right, talking about:
تدخل وتخرج من السيارة، تنظر إلى يمينك وتقول:
"Father, forgive me, for I have sinned," all day long -- you can't do it!
"يا أبتاه اغفر لي، لأني أخطأت،" كامل اليوم-- لا يمكن أن تفعل ذلك.
So we came up with some incredible initiatives,
لذا أتينا ببعض من المبادرات المدهشة،
engagements for our community and police to build that trust back.
التزامات لمجتمعنا والشرطة لكي نبني الثقة بين الطرفين من جديد.
We began to deal with our youth
بدأنا بالتعامل مع شبابنا
and with those who we consider are on the wrong side of the fence.
وأولئك الذين نعتبرهم على الجانب الخاطئ من السياج.
We knew we had an economic problem,
نعرف بأنه لدينا مشكلة قتصاديّة،
so we began to create jobs.
لذا بدأنا في توفير العمل.
We knew there was sickness in our community
نعرف بأنه هناك تفشي للمرض في مجتمعنا
and they didn't have access to proper medical care,
ولا يستطيع المواطنون الحصول على الرعاية الصحية اللازمة،
so we'd partner up.
لذا بدأنا في التعاون.
We got to that intersection and partnered up
بحثنا عن ذلك التقاطع وبدأنا في التعاون
with anybody that wanted to partner with us
مع أي شخص يريد أن يكون شريكا لنا
and talked about what we needed holistically,
وتكلمنا حول ما نريده بشكل كلي،
never thinking about the crime.
لا تفكّر في الجريمة أبدا.
Because at the end of the day,
لأنه في نهاية اليوم،
if we took care of the needs of the people,
إذا تمعنا في احتياجات الأشخاص،
if we got to the root cause,
إذا نظرنا إلى السبب بشكل جذري،
the crime would take care of itself.
سيتمّ حلّ الجريمة من تلقاء نفسها.
It would take care of itself.
سيتمّ حلّها من تلقاء نفسها.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And so, after three years of a four-and-a-half-year stint,
إذن، بعد 3 سنوات من أربع سنوات ونصف من التقصير،
we looked back and we looked over
نظرنا إلى ما مضى وأعدنا النظر
and found out that we were at a 40-year historical low:
وتبين بأننا عانينا من انخفاض تاريخي لمدة 40 سنة:
our crime numbers, our homicides --
عدد الجرائم وحالات القتل --
everything had dropped down, back to the 1970s.
شهد كل شيء انخفاضا منذ 1970.
And it might go back further,
وربما قبل ذلك،
but the problem is, we only started keeping data since 1970.
ولكن تكمن المشكلة أننا بدأنا في جمع البيانات منذ 1970.
Forty-year crime low, so much so, I had other commanders call me,
انخفاض في عدد الجرائم لمدة 40 سنة، اتصل بي قادة آخرون،
"Hey Mel, whatcha doin', man?
"مرحبا ميل، كيف حالك يا رجل؟"
Whatcha doin'? We gotta get some of that!"
كيف حالك؟ ينبغي أن نحصل على بعض من ذلك"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so we gave them some of that.
لذا أعطيناهم بعضا من ذلك.
And in a short period of time,
وفي مدة وجيزة،
the city went to a 30-year crime low.
انخفض عدد الجرائم لمدة 30 سنة
For the first time in 30 years, we fell, Baltimore city,
أول مرة لمدة 30 سنة، انخفضت، بحيّ بالتيمور،
to under 200 homicides -- 197 to be exact.
جرائم القتل إلى 200 - 197 بالضبط.
And we celebrated,
واحتفلنا،
because we had learned to become great servers,
لأننا تعلمنا كيف نصبح مقدمين أفضل للخدمة،
become great servers first.
مقدمين أفضل للخدمة أولاً.
But I gotta tell you this: these last few years,
ولكن عليّ أن أخبركم التالي: خلال هذه السنوات الأخيرة،
as much as we had learned
على قدر ما تعلمنا
to become great proactive police officers
كي نصبح رجال شرطة فاعلون
and great relational police officers rather than reactive,
وتربطنا علاقة وطيدة عوضاً عن ردّ الفعل،
these last years have disappointed me.
شعرت باليأس خلال هذه السنوات الأخيرة.
They have broken my heart.
لقد تم كسر قلبي.
The uprising still hurts.
مازلت أشعر بالألم من الثورة.
It still hurts my heart,
مازل قلبي يُؤلمني،
because truly I believe that it should've never happened.
لأنني أعتقد حقا بأنه لم يكن يجدر أن تحدث.
I believe it should've never happened
أعتقد أنه لم يكن يجدر أن تحدث
if we were allowed to continue along the vein that we were in,
إذا ما تمّ السماح لنا بمواصلة ما كنا نقوم به،
servicing our community,
لخدمة مجتمعنا،
treating them like human beings, treating them with respect,
ومعاملتهم كبشر، وباحترام،
loving on them first.
وأن نحبهم أولا.
If we continued in that vein,
لو واصلنا ما كنا نقوم به،
it would've never happened.
لم يكن ليحدث ما حدث.
But somehow, we went back to business as usual.
ولكن بطريقة ما رجعنا إلى التجارة كالعادة.
But I'm excited again!
ولكنني أشعر بالحماس مجددا.
I'm excited again, because now we have a police commissioner
أشعر بالحماس مجددا، لأنه أصبح لدينا نائب
who not only talks about community policing,
لا يتحدّث فقط حول الشرطة،
but he absolutely understands it,
ولكن يفهم ما يحصل داخل هذا المجتمع،
and more importantly, he embraces it.
والأهم من ذلك يقوم بالمعالجة.
So I'm very excited now.
أنا أشعر بالكثير من الحماس حاليا.
Listen, I'm excited about Baltimore today,
استمعوا، أنا أشعر بالحماس لبالتيمور اليوم،
because we, as many cities, I believe shall rise from the ashes.
لأنني أؤمن بأننا مثل جميع الأحياء في حاجة إلى الارتقاء.
I believe -- I truly believe --
أنا أؤمن بذلك -- أنا حقا أؤمن بذلك --
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
that we will be great again.
أننا سوف نصبح رائعين من جديد.
I believe,
أؤمن،
as we continue to wrap arms and continue to say,
لطالما سنواصل الاتحاد معا ونقول،
"We're in this together,"
"نحن في هذا معا"،
because it's not just an intersection:
لأنها ليست فقط مجرد تقاطع:
once we meet, we now gotta get on the same path for the same goals,
عندما نجتمع، ينبغي علينا الآن أن نكون معا ولدينا نفس الأهداف،
and this city will become great again.
وسيصبح هذا الحي رائعا من جديد.
This nation will become great again.
ستصبح الولاية رائعة من جديد.
Because we have the same goal: we all want peace.
لأنه لدينا نفس الهدف: جميعنا يريد السلام.
We all want respect for one another.
جميعنا يريد الاحترام المتبادل.
We all want love.
جميعنا يريد الحب.
And I believe we are back on that road,
وأؤمن حقا بأننا على الطريق الصحيح،
and I'm so excited about it.
وأنا متحمّس بشأن ذلك.
So listen, I thank you for giving me a few minutes of your time.
إذن استمعوا، أنا أشكركم على منحي بعض الدقائق من وقتكم.
God bless you all.
فليبارككم الرب جميعا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
God bless you.
فليبارككم الرب.